foreign
is a production of Frankie Freitas and
the internet Museum of filmography
[Music]
the date is November
2098 100 years into the future
the theme is a memorabilia show
dealing with antiques and collectibles
from the late 20th century
hello this is Frankie Freitas and
welcome to another week of holotalk
on the special broadcast we're going to
be taking a look at something I term
antiquarian holographica
which is the collection of holographic
memorabilia
at our show
we see where and first edition books
period maps and lithographs and in a
corner at the end of a long aisle is a
booth dealing exclusively with
holography
or imaginary booth has quite a selection
embossed Holograms including several
limited edition pieces produced back in
the late 1980s and 90s by a number of
prominent artists
a copy of the famous National Geographic
cover with the American Eagle
signatures and autographs of the early
movers and shakers in the field
Disney programs from early International
shows
first edition copies of many out of
print books on holography
and there's a real attention getter as
well
actual helium neon laser that the person
in the booth tells you really works that
is if you can find a place that still
uses electricity for power
our little scenario is not that
far-fetched many of the items related to
holography then we pass over as
insignificant stuffed into our desk
drawers and filing cabinets
will someday be looked upon as period
pieces worthy of collection
and since we can be fairly certain that
we won't be around to attend our little
imaginary convention in 2098
why not make the most of the time that
we do have by attempting to put together
an impressive collection of future
holographic memorabilia
whole talk receives quite a few emails
on a regular basis from its listeners
and many of those emails are asking for
specific information relating to
collecting
one person wrote asking for information
concerning a specific embossed hologram
and how to acquire one for their
collection another from Europe spoke of
the writer's pride in the collection of
books and other printed materials all
related to the field of holography but
added that they were concerned that it
was not complete could it be I wondered
that collecting holographic related
items was catching on around the globe
the answer to that question appears to
be in the affirmative yes there is
collecting going on and the real
surprise is that it may prove to be the
most active aspect of the field
there appears to be a fever that goes
hand in hand with the art of collecting
collectors can sometimes go through
extreme trouble searching out materials
and nowhere are those materials more new
and exciting than holography
for a field celebrating its first few
Decades of existence there is a
multitude of collecting possibilities
including tracking down books and
related articles that extend much
further back in time than just a few
decades
there is a rich history and many
centuries of Art and science behind it
some of it extending back into the 16th
and 17th centuries all of it relating to
holography today
this broadcast of holotalk is devoted to
what I call antiquarian holographica
searching out the Articles books posters
and Holograms from around the world to
add to one's Personal Collection of of
holographic future memorabilia
the mission of this broadcast is to
provide a solid foundation for starting
one's own archive on photography
for future Generations who will look
back in time not only Through The Eyes
of a collector
but a keeper of antiquarian holographica
that's with any new
important
an ultimate destination for your
collection
will you concentrate on books and
publications
embossed Holograms
posters and commemorative of exhibits
all of the above and more
remember there is little if any
background material available
concerning collecting holography
so much of the groundwork leg work and
Pen work along with many hours of
research will have to be done by you The
Collector
more you know the more your collection
will benefit
since much of your knowledge will show
through in your aesthetic judgments and
decisions
whatever your plan is for reaching reach
your goal
it should never be executed in a
haphazard way
decisions should be made intelligently
and with great care as to what is worth
having the honor of being part of your
collection
remember this isn't clutter or garage
sale mentality we're talking about here
but a systematic recording of the
history of holography
let's take a look at what a typical
collection might contain
we'll start with Holograms
embossed Holograms would be represented
from around
dark images and images that are unique
Holograms such as bird and rocks from
John Kaufman
magic teeth by Harriet kazden silver
which came with its own slip case with
the art of signature on it or Stargate
by Dan Schweitzer
would be a central part of any
collection
there are also magazines books book
satellogues brochures that have
holograms on their cover or inside the
issue
these printed pieces and the embossed
Holograms would be carefully placed in
Black sleeves numbered identified
stored carefully away from thumbing
Curiosity Seekers
sets such as the ET stickers from
Hershey recent species would round out
the collection
a unique ET set would have all nine
images on one untouched sheet of foil
these are much harder to combine so
would be valued more for a collection
the new photopolymer Holograms would
also be considered a collectible the
reflection Holograms produced on film
and sold throughout retail outlets
across the U.S are also a consideration
Publications
some newspaper and magazine articles
along with newsletters and press
releases are filed as Originals whenever
possible
or add Xerox copies
is the collector's main effort however
to eventually track down original
printed materials to eventually replace
the deluxe copies
most magazine and newsletter Publishers
have back issues available in stock and
will send you a copy if requested to do
so
of course having an original issue
versus a Xerox is really a decision made
by The Collector based on individual
preference
in the future the original will be the
most sought after so the decision
remains with the collector and their
long-term goals
books
many books would be represented dealing
with holography and its branches of
lasers light and even philosophy
one thing is certain books are an
expensive part of collecting
most books dealing with holography are
not old enough or published in large
enough numbers to be easily found on The
Used Book Rack
holography is a technical science and
Technical manuals can run up quite a bit
fortunately there are enough
over-the-counter inexpensive soft covers
to keep a collector busy for a long time
most bookstores will gladly special
order titles for you although some may
put an additional finders fee on the
final cost
but these charges are usually minimum
first editions especially those that are
out of print are a collector's dream and
a field unto itself
creme de La Creme of book collecting
whether you need first editions or
simply a well-handed later Edition is a
matter of preference
first editions accumulate the most value
as the years go by
so looking to the future is a
consideration that must be eventually
confronted
letters and autographs
Collectibles too
letters are more of a personal
collectible since many shouldn't be put
on display or passed around
a letter or document written entirely in
the hand of its author is
holograph
a standalone signature is an autograph
the letters I have on file are obviously
due to the whole talk program and a
newsletter that I published back in the
80s
but if you were to write to a
holographer I'm sure they would be glad
to write a short note back
since I don't know of any holographers
Who currently need to have protection
from crowds of admirers I'm sure your
request would be flattering
remember use discretion displaying the
letter note card or autograph
and don't pass over the beauty of the
envelope many foreign stamps as well as
us are truly works of art
quality and feel of the paper the design
and printing of the letterhead the
penmanship get a feel for all these
things
many posters announcements and catalogs
are still available through holography
museums Galleries and manufacturers
many years ago through neglect I lost an
original poster for the inaugural tour
of the New York museum of philography
through the Looking Glass
don't make the same mistake
either put it on the wall or keep it in
a cylinder
equipment catalogs are highly
collectible not only do they show photos
of the errors existing technology
but many give technical drawings also
Newport research catalogs have photos
and blueprints for every piece of
equipment
as the field progresses and mirrors
lenses and filters are gradually
replaced by fiber optic and holographic
Optical elements and whatever will come
after that
if catalogs will take on an air of
nostalgia
just call a company and ask for a
catalog
tell them your 300 plus employee company
grossed 150 million last year and you'll
get it overnight express
how about patents well the way things
are going the patents may become more
famous than many Holograms
you can call the patent office in
Washington DC and receive for a nominal
fee all the patents applied for and
granted in the field of holography
patents make a great addition to any
collection
overall collecting should be an
enjoyable and rewarding experience
you may have a collection started
already and just never looked at it as
so
go through your drawers and file
cabinets bookshelves Etc and begin
sorting things out you may surprise at
what's there
keep an eye open at all times for
Holograms and articles books and
magazines
with the interesting holography
continuing at an evident accelerating
pace and individuals who began their
interest in holography several years ago
now becoming more sophisticated in their
appreciation of the medium
the time is right for a blossoming of
interest in collecting works of
holography
however while the most prominent artists
in the field are beginning to find
clientele willing to make substantial
investments in their work
the majority of these works are priced
beyond the means of the average
enthusiasts
this leaves an area completely void
which is waiting to participate in
collecting Holograms
It is believed that we may begin to fill
that void by suggesting that a would-be
collector Begin by concentrating his or
her efforts on building a collection of
low-cost and in many cases no cost
readily available embossed Holograms
now one may immediately remark that if
embossed Holograms are low cost and
readily available
what would the collecting interest be
to answer this it must be pointed out
that although many embossed Holograms
are low in cost there are many that are
difficult to find
awesome since several holographic
artists have created works that were
limited edition embossed Holograms
it is possible to own a work with only a
modest investment by such artists as
Harry Cassidy silver John Kaufman Dan
Schweitzer among others
there are a few embossed Holograms that
are becoming harder and harder to find
they are becoming rare
however once located and older out of
print limited run embossed hologram is a
treasure to own and view
it is truly a collector's piece
what does a beginning collector need to
know
let's break it down
it would be possible to have a
combination of any single group
classification with any single subgroup
let's clarify and Define each group and
subgroup
on groups are group one
2D graphic stickers
these are the images that are line
drawings or graphics and are essentially
flat surface pictures
usually another 2D flat surface image
will appear a short depth away from the
front image
the second image was usually a neutral
field
many Holograms of this type use the
background of stars a good example for
collection purposes would be the famous
UT stickers found in packages of Reese's
Pieces
the second group would be 3D images
now these embossed images are the same
as a regular Rainbow or white light
transmission hologram that uses a
three-dimensional object be it real or
abstract as its image
a good example would be one of the
National Geographic covers
subgroups now these groups are the
subgroups of either group one which is
the 2D Graphics sticker or group two
3D images
subgroup a
Standalone Holograms
these Holograms are usually packaged
individually with the Hologram itself
acting as the end product an example
would be any retail hologram sold only
for its own purpose
subgroup B packaging Holograms
embossed Holograms included in the
packaging design of a consumer-related
product or its packaging materials
usually designed to attract or call
attention to the product and enhance the
product's visibility and or appeal
also used by companies to promote itself
as future oriented or having a
forward-looking vision an example would
be the hologram on a box
for a camera
subgroup C
artistic Holograms
these are usually limited edition pieces
created by an established holographic
artist with the Masters made in the
artist studio lab or rental facility and
then mass-produced by embossing
similar to a lithograph made from the
pain
an example would be how it casually
silver magic teeth which had a run of 1
750 pieces
and was offered in a sleeve that
contained the artist's signature
subgroup d
experimental prototype Holograms
this type of embossed hologram is valued
as a collectible for the simple reason
that something about it makes it one of
a kind
an embossed hologram that was an
artist's proof and still contained Crop
Marks and cut lines
would make that piece unique from the
others that were to follow for retail
sale
while a person can certainly become
overwhelmed by the sheer number of
embossed Holograms that have flooded the
market since their Inception
with a certain amount of skill and work
can become possible to build quite an
impressive collection of embossed
holographic images
with regards to acceptance of
Holograms within the holographic
Community a purest attitude once
prevailed in the collective minds of
holographic artists
their initial concern about the viewing
of their work now removed from the
hermetically sealed environment of the
holography Galleries and museums and now
out on the street with the general
public
was soon found to ring true
I still recall to my horror a group of
people Outdoors under Cloudy Skies
exclaiming wow that's neat at the site
of the smeared gray image of the
National Geographic cover
and one can almost picture the balding
agent groovy art director equipping it
doesn't do anything for me as he holds a
beautifully executed holograph under his
fluorescent drafting lamp
the fabric is wearing thin on the issue
of holograms not being viable because
they're not visible under anything less
than ideal lighting conditions I have
always made this out to be a plus
since it only added two rather than
subtracted from holography somewhat
mystical appeal
take an embossed hologram that was
carefully produced and copied place it
in an appropriate frame with matting
take care to make sure it is illuminated
properly and you have a hologram that
will stand up visually to anything
produced in limited quantities on glass
plates
only a Discerning Eye or someone with
knowledge of the holographic process
itself would find discrepancies
embossed Holograms are beautiful and fun
to collect and for a modest investment
of your time and money
you can build an impressive collection
of holograms for display